我开始相信你说的神了
I begin to believe in your gods.
我命令他们坚守阵地 但他们逃跑了
I ordered them to stand ground but they fled.
您想让我受到怎样的惩罚
What punishment would you have me inflict?
他夺走了我的东西
He took something from me.
那我也要夺走他的东西
And I would have something in return.
说错一个字 就等着受苦吧
If errant word falls from mouth, only suffering will follow.
来吧 亲爱的
Come, my love.
她是罗马人
She stands a Roman.
我现在只是奴隶
I stand nothing but a slave.
你给我恢复理智
You will regain sense.
失去理智的是你
It is you who has no sense.
多纳
Donar!
- 该死的叛徒 - 你疯了吗
- Fucking traitor. - Have you lost mind?
卡斯特斯是来帮忙的
Castus came to aid!
我们必须确保剩下的人安全撤到山上
We must see all that remain to safety of the ridge.
快走 不要回头
Move quickly! And do not turn back!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
斯巴达克斯不是傻子
Spartacus is no fool.
你觉得他会在大风雪中
You expect him to wait in driven snow
等你到来 给他致命一击吗
for you to arrive and announce his end?
那正是我所期待的
That is exactly what I expect.
《斯巴达克斯：诅咒者之战》
《必死无疑》
清点下死者 看看损失了多少人
Give count to those who have fallen! I would have number!
诸神逼着我们一路走向奥林匹斯山
The gods march us halfway to fucking Olympus,
就为了往我们头上撒尿吗
only to piss on us from atop a wall.
我们必须找到新的出路
We must make new attempt.
我们不要默不作声地当胆小鬼
While we do not quit in silence,
我们要发起震天动地的进攻
but march with thunder threating the heavens.
拿脑袋去撞他们的墙吗
And see old men strom their wall?
直到最后一个女人和孩子
Until last woman and child,
非叫它倒塌不可
and see it to ruin.
我不能冒这样的险
I can not risk futher resource.
克拉苏就是要逼我们无路可走
Crassus has turning us from warming moves
踏进他的陷阱
into his traps.
而你会因愚蠢的举动
And you would be slaughter
丢掉小命
in foolish action.
我只是想在山上找条路
I but seek path on this fucking Ridge.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
克拉苏的军队从隘口那边过来了
Crassus' army approaches from the mountain pass.
不能打仗的都撤到安全地方去
Move all those who cannot fight to safe distance.
剩下的准备迎战
See the others to weapons.
让这个腰缠万贯的人瞧瞧
We will show the man forged of gold
想杀我们得付出什么代价
the cost of our lives.
用罗马人的血把他妈的雪地染红
We shall see Roman blood upon fucking snow!
或者光荣战死 血洒白野
Or our own in glorious death!
别动
Hold!
都冷静下
Calm yourselves!
你这话对打仗没好处
Your words move against purpose.
我们得主动出击
We must press attack,
以免陷入被动
before his army washes over us.
他们没打算进攻
They do not intend to advance.
诸神还给了你预言未来的能力吗
The gods hold you privy to the future now, do they?
我只是有过不幸的经历而已
I am but familiar with unfortunate past.
我还在色雷斯时 曾在罗马辅备军中服役
I served in the Roman auxiliary when I was yet of Thrace.
克拉苏的人马没有排出进攻阵形
Crassus' men did not fall to battle formation.
但他们人数占绝对优势
But they hold advantage of numbers.
为什么不把我们一举消灭
Why pause short of blood?
要等他们的将军来了才动手
They but await their commander.
军队在山上驻扎好了
The legion takes position upon the ridge?
正在按您的命令在前线安置大帐
With your praetorium to be set at forward position, as commanded.
准备好了就迅速来报
Break urgent word when it's prepared.
我要亲眼见证此次大胜
I would lay eyes upon war's end at nearest opportunity.
遵命
Imperator.
我有急事耽搁了
I have been delayed from appointed hour by pressing need.
十分抱歉
Apologies.
没事
None expected.
我知道您军务缠身
I'm sure you this much needed of you, upon victory.
恺撒怎么样
How fares Caesar?
还在舔伤口
He yet licks his wounds.
或者这么说吧 花天酒地买安慰
Or rather drops coin for more pleasing form to apply balming tongue.
感谢你不负使命
Gratitude for seeing duties to completion,
没有沉溺于私欲
and not falling prey to baser desires of your own.
男人行乐要选对时机
A man must choose proper moment to seize pleasure.
而我唯您马首是瞻
Mine is forever entwined with your own.
听你这么说我很感动
I stand moved by sentiment.
你最近的所作所为也让我很满意
As I do by the way you've afforded yourself of late.
您过奖了 统帅
You honor me, Imperator.
你的言行值得褒奖
You honor yourself in deed and action.
我想让你以这种心态迎接新的任务
I would see such spirit greet newest command.
全凭您吩咐
Speak it, and see it done.
我想让这个箱子从我面前消失
I wish this chest spirited from sight.
任务虽然简单 却意义非凡
A simple task, yet one of grave importance.
应该把它放哪儿
Where shall I place it?
打开看看 自己决定
Crack seal, and make own decision.
我的盔甲
My armor...
斯巴达克斯时日无多
The hour rushes to Spartacus' end.
我要你继续代我行使权力
I would have my Word and my Will
再次与我并肩作战
once more at my side upon final battle.
父子齐上阵
I would have my son.
我愿与您同上战场
As I would stand with you.
父亲
Father.
好好穿戴上
See yourself to proper dress.
未来还有很多事需要商讨
There is much of our future to turn upon discussion.
原来你也是血肉之躯
You prove yourself yet mortal.
一点小伤不要在意
A scratch, all but forgotten.
我给你换绷带
I will see to fresh bandage.
美酒 还有你的软玉温香
Wine and the warmth of your thighs
就足够安抚我了
is all comfort needed.
至于血债嘛 等到那一天
Blood shall wait upon the day I draw it from those
我宰了那帮贼人自能偿还
who have dared move against me.
他们一定吓得五体投地
And they shall tremble with fear...
正如我拜倒在朱庇特的胯下
As I now tremble before Jupiter's cock...
搬过来
Vacate!
越快越好
Quick as you can!
暴风雪要来了
A storm is coming.
寒风可是要冻死人的
And with it death upon frozen wind.
暴风雪是要来了
Storm certain, yes.
不过还没到
Yet not its hour...
罗马人都到了眼皮底下
You would move to fuck,
你居然还有心情做爱
with Rome's might breathing upon our necks?
就算要死
If I for afterlife,
我也要死在你的胯下
I take memory of your cock inside me.
还是先别想我们自己了
Let us turn thought from ourselves,
干点正事吧
and see them towards deeper needs.
你这口气跟斯巴达克斯一样
Your words sound as Spartacus.
是我的真心话
They are my own.
听不听由你
Heed them as you will.
你个操蛋的叛徒
You traitorous fuck!
多纳 纳美特斯人和我们数百名兄弟
Donar, Nemetes and hundreds of our brothers
都死在了城里
lay dead in the city.
你他妈的还有饭吃
Yet you take fucking meal!
谢谢
Gratitude.
你的炖汤真是倒胃口
Your stew was turning stomach.
混蛋西利西亚人
Fucking Cilician shit!
布瑞克提斯
Brictius!
给我滚
Fall from fucking sight.
你还护着这婊子
If you were not Agron's boy,
你要不是艾力冈的人 我早就揍扁你了
you would stand as bloodied for shielding this little cunt.
有本事的话
Place Agron from thought,
别管艾力冈 来揍我啊
if you believe your cock of a size.
别看你人小 气势还挺足
For such a little man you speak as if a titan.
别让我后悔帮你
Do not move me to regret coming to aid.
布瑞克提斯是头畜生
Brictius is a dim brute,
但他说的也有道理
but his tongue carries knowledge.
我是西利西亚人
I stand a Cilician,
躲不开叛徒之名
and by tether of name a traitor.
谁也不该为别人的行为负责
None should be darkened by shadow of another's actions.
这不重要
A thing of no importance.
命运指引我来到这里
I find myself where the fates have led.
有你陪伴 那是几辈子修不来的福气
And call it blessing to find you there as well.
双手被缚 浑身是血 还不忘花言巧语
In chains and bloodied, yet still attempting to flatter.
我只想尽可能活长一点
I attempt but to live life to the fullest measure.
我想要拿起武器对抗克拉苏
And would take arms against Crassus
从而活下去
to continue doing so.
你想打仗
You wish to fight?
当初我杀了罗马人才赢得你的信任 对吧
Killing Romans was how I gained your trust, was it not?
如果我能杀死更多罗马人
Perhaps if enough fall to my blade,
你的兄弟们总有一天也会信任我
your brothers shall one day be so moved...
这不是我说了算的 不过…
It is a decision removed from my hands. But...
我感到很欣慰
know that thought is well received.
没想到还能见到你
I did not think to lay eyes upon you again.
我也是
Nor I you.
真是造化弄人
The gods mock us both.
你在城里的时候是那么勇敢
Used rich day of your bravery within the city,
冒生命危险救你的人
risking life to save your people.
还不是别无选择
I still absent choice.
如今我算是体会到了
Position known well of late.
你现在还活着
You are still of this world.
但再不吃饭 恐怕就不行了
Yet shall slip from it if you do not eat.
给更值得的人吃吧
See it to one more deserving.
你想博取同情吗
Do you seek to be pitied?
我什么也不想
I seek nothing.
我什么也不是
I am but ash.
那携雨之使者
The remains of heart's flame,
血洗了我的城市
cooled by the Bringer of Rain,
把我的生活搅得天翻地覆
who brought death to my city
让我心如死灰
and tore me from the life I knew.
而那个克拉苏
Smothered by Crassus,
解开我的锁链
who cast me off in chains
却拿我满足蛮子的兽欲
for the pleasure of a savage.
你经历了痛苦
You have known pain.
体会了失去
And loss.
和我们当中的很多人一样
A misfortune shared by many among us.
你是怎么熬过去的
How do you move past it?
我也问过很多次同样的问题
That's a question I've asked many times.
活下去
Live.
找到答案
And help provide answer.
恺撒很喜欢庆功会上的牡蛎
Caesar favored oysters in his celebration.
我要在我的庆功会上吃到城里最好的
I would have the finest city has to offer towards my own.
你父亲又看重你了
Your father graces you again with favor.
那是我赢来的
A thing well earned.
我不是以前那个撅嘴撒娇的小男孩了
I no longer the "Pouting boy" of days past.
我成为了父亲一直想让我成为的人
The man my father has always longed for me to become.
我只希望萨比努斯还活着
I but wish Sabinus were yet among us.
你说他会为我骄傲吗
Do you think he would gaze upon me with pride?
他很爱护你 不是吗
He held you to heart, did he not?
你曾经也是
As you once did.
你大可不必在意这些
Your path carries you far from such concerns.
斯巴达克斯必会灭亡
Spartacus shall fall,
而你将去征服更多的土地
and you shall rise to conquer foreign lands,
建立丰功伟业
and build upon your name.
远离曾经关心过你的人
Far from those who once cared for you.
我渴望用胜利和荣耀
I yearn to honor the name of Crassus
为克拉苏家族增光添彩
with victory and laurels.
不过等讨伐完叛贼
Yet after rebellion is struck
我要在这里扎根
I shall remain rooted firmly upon current ground.
你不跟我们回罗马了
You are not to return to Rome with us?
我奉命在希留爱沙为父亲操持大事
I will be tasked with securing my father's concerns within Sinuessa,
等年龄到了再接过护民官的头衔
until I reach proper age for title of Tribune.
这是很重要的职责
A duty of great import.
而你要留下来帮我
One you shall aid me in.
我要留在希留爱沙
I am to remain in Sinuessa?
就在这座宅子里
Within this very villa.
我父亲可以让你当女管家
My father grants you title of vilica
监管所有伺候我的奴仆
to oversee all who serve me beneath storied roof.
同时在人生路上继续安抚我 指引我
And to see comforting hand continue to guide me in life's journey.
是你让我悬崖勒马
One that drew me from edge of dire precipice.
我欠你太多 克芮
I owe you much, Kore.
等我有了时间 我要好好补偿你
And soon I'll have the leisure of time to indulge repayment.
统帅
Imperator.
您的大帐已经设好
Your praetorium stands ready upon the ridge.
叫旗手来
Call for my standard bearer.
遵命
Imperator.
打扰一下 主人
Apologies, Dominus.
晚饭准备好了
I have prepared afternoon meal
我要吃的是叛贼的血肉
I have appetite towards bloodier repast.
抱歉 主人
Again, apologies.
有些话我想跟您说
Yet I would also break needed words.
有话快说
Well, shatter them quickly,
我马上就要走了
or see them to ground I once stood upon.
我真的要留在希留爱沙伺候提比略吗
Is it true I am to serve Tiberius in Sinuessa?
是他亲口跟你说的吗
By his tongue did news fall upon ear?
这孩子转达我的话之前也不好好想想
The boy carries my word yet spills it absent consideration.
我本想在更私密的场合先跟你谈谈的
I had meant to share thought with you in more intimate fashion.
我也要倾吐我的忧虑
As I would share with you troubled mind,
以及其缘由
and cause of it
所有人整装待命 统帅
All stands upon command, Imperator.
只可惜时与愿违
Time conspires against will of the heart.
等战斗胜利后我们再好好谈谈吧
We shall break words again when battle is won,
到那时你就不会再忧伤流泪了
will see tears evaporate beneath warming sun of deeper intent.
来吧 我们到山里演一出戏
Come, let us make show of presence upon ridge.
我要让叛贼头子知道什么叫末日
I'd have the Rebel King know what doom falls upon him.
克拉苏居然支起了看台
Crassus erects pulvinus,
就好像这儿是风雪竞技场
as if we fight for his entertainment
我们以命相搏是为他取乐
upon snow of fucking arena.
那他将亲眼目睹
Then he shall behold what miracles
角斗士创造的鲜血奇观
of blood a gladiator is yet capable of.
你说的好像所有人都是角斗士
You speak as though all stand so.
我们是就够了
The ways of us do.
他们可都是我们亲手训练出来的
Passed on from our very hands.
可要面对夹击我们的大军 人数太少了
Too few to make difference against hordes we are pressed between.
克雷斯的信念没有错
Crixus is not wrong in his belief.
我们一次次地完成了不可能的壮举
We have done the impossible, time upon time.
但靠的是战术 而不是蛮力
Yet by inspired tactic, not brute force.
你是怎么想的
What are the lay of your thoughts?
克拉苏占据绝对上风 因此过分大胆
Crassus has become overly bold by advantage he holds.
为了方便观赏预期的大胜
He places his praetorium forward of proper position,
他的大帐放得过于靠前
to better view anticipated victory.
或许我们应该去拜访他
Perhaps we should pay visit,
告诉他这一致命错误
and explain fatal error.
大帐安置得这么靠前 难道守军不会更多吗
Does not closer position suggest heavier guard surrounding praetorium?
风暴到来之前 狂风会吹个没完
The wind grows restless in advance of storm.
待夜幕降临 只要去的人不多
By night's fall, it shall serve as cloak
我们就能神不知鬼不觉地摸进去
if our number is not swollen beyond intent.
要多少人
How many?
只要我们之中的精锐
Only the most skilled among us.
我们必须像毒蛇一样发起攻击 又快又准
We must strike as the serpent, fast and sure.
如果克拉苏死在我们手下
If Crassus falls to our venom,
他的军团将会群龙无首 成为一盘散沙
his legions will froth and foam absent proper command.
对科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯时这招很管用
A plan well served against Cossinius and Furius.
明明可以让他经历人间炼狱
You would send a sleeping man to the afterlife
你却要在睡梦中去抹他脖子
when he could awaken to a nightmare.
我们所有人一起来 杀个痛快岂不更好
A sea of death as our entire army crashes upon him.
这么庞大的阵容在行动之前就会被发现
Such a force would be discovered in advance of purpose,
我们将优势尽失 连小孩子都能看出来
and advantage lost. A thing a child could see.
你当我是小孩子吗
You would brand me as such?
是我失言了 兄弟
Words foolishly chosen, brother.
随我一道去
Stay by my side,
等克拉苏从这个世界消失后
and when Crassus is falls from this world
他的大军也将很快烟消云散
we shall see his legions swiftly follow.
注意观察 随时报告
Lay eyes and report.
我们应该在周围看守 以防有人逃走
We shall hold perimeter against escape.
伟大的克拉苏今晚是无路可逃了
There shall be none for the mighty Crassus this night.
多纳
Donar...
他身上刻的是什么
What is carved upon his flesh?
必死无疑
Death is undeceivable.
快走
Come on.
妮维雅
Naevia!
快来
Come on.
撤回营地
Fall back to the camp!
逃吧 你们这些懦夫
Flee, you fucking coward!
保持阵型
In formation!
克雷斯
Crixus!
进攻
Advance!
斯巴达克斯逃脱了
Spartacus slips from snare?
还有跟随他的一小撮人
Along with a small clutch of his men.
让他吃点苦头吧
Let him feel the sting of his wounds,
尝尝聪明反被聪明误的滋味
and reflect upon the mind that inflicts them.
把提比略和恺撒从睡梦中叫起来
Raise Tiberius and Caesar from peaceful slumber.
阴谋诡计已经玩够了
The time for ploy and deception draws to an end.
你恺撒终于死而复生了
Caesar at last rises from the dead.
你也摆脱了惩罚的阴影
As you from specter of punishment.
凌晨时分叫醒我们有什么要紧事
What draws concern in advance of morning sun?
天一亮我就向米利亚峰进军
I depart for Melia Ridge upon dawn's break.
我早就想这么做了
A move long in coming.
我们这就…
Let us hasten arrival
我要你去集结希留爱沙城内的军队
I'd have you pause to gather remaining troops yet in Sinuessa.
到时你听提比略命令
Fall to command beneath Tiberius
月升之前与我会合
and join me before moon greets us.
难道不该是夺下希留爱沙的人带兵吗
Should not the man who took Sinuessa lead them?
怎么要剑都拿不稳的小子担此大任
Not a boy prone to losing his sword?
你觉得我对你的感激还不够多吗
You find my gratitude short in the coming?
水涨船高的债钱是谁给你的
The abundant coin awarded to keep head above rising debts?
是谁让梅泰勒斯去罗马宣扬你的英勇事迹的
Tales of bravery dispatched with Metellus to ply ears of Rome?
还有专门为你开的庆功会
Celebration thrown in your honor...
还是由这个你所不齿的人主持的
presented by the man you disrespect.
过去的慷慨我从未忘记
I need no reminder of past generosity.
我仅仅只是提供建议
I merely offer suggestion.
而我仅仅只是发号施令
And I merely give command.
而我刚才命令你
As I commanded your placement
守在城墙后面 听我的指示行动
behind city walls to move as my instrument.
夺下这座城的人是我
I took this city.
夺走斯巴达克斯性命的也会是我
As I shall take Spartacus' life,
还有我身边的儿子
with my son close at hand.
那在这辉煌的荣耀中
And where shall honored Caesar find himself
恺撒又居于何处呢
in the midst of such glories?
一视同仁
At equal distance.
只要他别我行我素
If he but removes himself from his own path.
遵命 统帅
He falls to command, Imperator.
按我说的做
Stay true to course,
到时候少不了你的好处
and we shall seize the heavens as promised.
我们山上见
I shall greet you upon the ridge.
风卷残云
Move with haste,
嗜血杀敌
and thirst for enemy's blood.
瞧瞧
Here we stand.
我官复原职
Title restored to me.
你又该卑躬屈膝了
And you beneath heel.
走路当心 小子
You mind your step, boy.
很多巨人就因为太自大了
Many a giant has tumbled to the afterlife,
以为摔不死 结果一跟头去了黄泉
believing himself too big to fall.
召集军队
Assemble the men.
听命行事
As commanded.
这该死的屋子里就没人睡觉吗
Does no one ever sleep in this fucking house?
对不起
Apologies.
我听到你们在争执 就过来了
I was drawn by argument.
然后你就躲在暗处偷看
And you lurked in the shadow to witness it?
随着提比略官复要职
It is a dangerous thing to be removed from them.
要摆脱他们都是很危险的了
Since Tiberius is restored to imagined power.
你竟敢说主人闲话
You rattle tongue against your master?
我只是悄悄说出我们共同的威胁
I but whisper of common threat.
希望能够消除我们共同的担忧
And means of striking it from mutual concern.
您愿意听我说 非常感谢
Gratitude for private audience.
这次谈话我必将守口如瓶
I would not have it known that we break words.
你现在还什么都没说
They yet remain whole within fucking mouth.
你也看到了我心情不好
You have witnessed foul mood.
可别再拐弯抹角 给我火上浇油
Do not deepen it with mystery and obscured purpose.
近来很多事情都变了
Much has changed of late.
我视同己出的那个孩子
The boy that I once held to breast as a child
如今已经不再是当年的黄毛小子了
has now grown far removed from the tenderness of youth.
现在的他 已经威胁到了
The thing he has become now threatens
你我所期望的前程
to turn us both from desired position.
那小子究竟伤你多深
How deeply have you been pierced by the boy?
您只用知道我受伤很深
It must be enough to know that I stand wounded.
正如提比略官复原职给您造成的伤害
As you have been by Tiberius' return to exalted title.
这么说你有计划了
So you have thought, do you?
目的就是抚平伤痛
Towards dressing such grievous injuries?
我很早就应该付诸行动了
One that I should have birthed to action long ago.
那就行动吧
Then do so.
不要把我恺撒牵扯进来
And leave Caesar far removed from plots and schemes.
如果剿灭斯巴达克斯有提比略的功劳
If victory over Spartacus is shared with Tiberius,
只怕他们父子之间再无嫌隙可乘
I fear their bond will be forged in permanence.
打开天窗说亮话
Cut circle with straightest line,
你就说要我怎么做吧
and give voice to what you would have of me.
知道你还活着
It lifts heart.
我真是松了一口气
To know you are yet among us.
多亏你救我一命
Fate owed to you.
克雷斯说是你将我背回营地
Crixus tells of how you carried me upon back.
换了谁都会这么做
It is what any of us would do.
别的勇士受伤也一样
For another warrior.
她需要休息
She yet requires rest.
她可以安心养伤了
She will have it, for a time.
这段时间暴风雪势头渐猛
Storm grows with the passing hour,
罗马军队无法进军
making Roman advance unlikely.
我不希望有人讲话打扰她休息
I would see her undisturbed by the gale of words as well.
现在变成这样了吗
Is this how it is to be now?
我们总是这样互相看不惯
Are we always to find ourselves churning against one another,
就跟当年我们在巴蒂塔斯家做奴隶一样
as when we were yet slaves to Batiatus?
那时候你的胆子可没这么小
Forgotten days when you were yet of bolder mind.
如果我们全军出动进攻克拉苏
If we had moved with proper force against Crassus
结果又会怎样
What would have been result?
假设我们走了那条路
Peer into future of path not taken
说说看你认为会怎样
and break where you believe it to lead.
妮维雅就不会血洒当场
Ground not stained with Naevia's blood.
只怕有上千个弟兄要抛洒热血了
You would see it but joined by thousands.
我会英勇战斗
I would but fight.
壕沟围墙还有什么战术可讲
Wall and trench block forward tactic.
你跟克拉苏玩策略
Your plot against Crassus
已经证明了你没有他那么狡猾
you have been bested by more devious mind.
我们应该让所有人拿上武器
We should place sword in every hand
只要一息尚存 就要跟罗马狗干到底
yet with strength to lift it and fall upon the Romans.
我们的四周是悬崖峭壁
We are bound by canyon walls,
侧翼包抄是行不通的
absent hope of flanking maneuver.
面对兵力装备占优 军纪严明的罗马军
To face superior numbers possessed of armor and discipline
我们只能自寻死路
will gain us nothing but our own deaths.
那就让罗马狗看看 我们如何视死如归
Then let the Romans see how we fucking embrace it.
正如我们在沙场上学到的
As we were taught to upon the sands.
你又在说废话了
You return to spent argument.
我们之中并没有多少角斗士
Few among us stand as gladiators.
他们可不想壮烈赴死
They do not pray for a glorious death.
不 他们盼着有人带头
No. They pray to be led.
我绝不会带着他们去送死
I will not march my people to the afterlife!
我也绝不会让罗马狗从背后捅刀子
And I will not die with a Roman sword in my back!
我去召集志同道合的人
I will gather those of a like mind
出兵迎战克拉苏
and press attack upon Crassus.
你胆敢违抗命令
You will fall to command
你还真当自己是神了
You are not a fucking God!
我不会听凭你指手画脚
And I do not heed to voice upon high!
克雷斯
Crixus!
你们都他妈的疯了吗
Have you fallen from fucking reason?!
这话还是问你的领袖吧
A question better posed to your leader.
克雷斯
Crixus!
现在不是争吵的时候
Now is not time for quarrel!
大风已经吹翻了医护帐篷
Medicus tent has been struck by rising winds!
暴雪将至
The storm approaches!
必须带他们到掩蔽处
See those exposed to shelter!
诸神这是要在我们进攻之前
The Gods threaten to wipe clean the blight of rebellion
先行扫清叛贼啊
before we're able to mount attack.
那我们明日一早就出兵
Then we shall rise with morning sun,
把诸神赦免的叛贼清扫干净
and finish any they have chosen to spare.
恺撒
Caesar.
我好像没听到
I did not hear welcoming horns
欢迎提比略及其军队前来的号角
announcing Tiberius' approach with balance of men.
他们都没来
They stand as absent as his presence.
你应该随军行动
You were to aid him in troops' movement.
我说得不够清楚吗
Was command not clear?
我听得一清二楚
As the air between us.
但有更紧急的事
Yet pressing matter clouds thought,
我只能抗命前来了
and thunder sound toward higher duty...
你竟敢带她来这儿
You would bring her here,
来到战场
upon field of battle?
对不起 主人
Apologies, Dominus.
是我苦苦哀求恺撒
Caesar but bends to tearful plea.
只因我心中哀痛 要一吐为快
From mournful tongue that must break word.
退下吧
Leave us.
恺撒
Caesar!
你为何不遵守命令待在北门
Why did you not wait at northern gate as ordered?
抱歉
Apologies.
我也舍不得离开你 可是有急事
Urgent task drew me from the pleasure of your company.
我父亲要是知道你不服从命令 肯定不高兴
My father will not stand pleased by word of insubordination.
换作我 现在就不去找他
I would pause before seeking audience.
统帅正忙着…
The Imperator is otherwise taken...
见他最心爱的奴隶呢
by presence of beloved slave.
克芮
Kore?
你违反军令就是为了带女人来军营吗
You disobey command to bring a fucking woman to encampment?
她非常急切地要与你父亲谈话
She was desperate to break word with your father.
我实在不忍心拒绝给她见面的机会
I could not find heart to deny her opportunity to gain his ear.
她有何事如此急迫
What concerns so move her?
那就是他们的秘密了 不是吗
Ah, that's the mystery, is it not?
不过别着急
Yet calm rattled nerve.
你是父亲的好儿子 她说了什么
I'm certain father will share with trusted son
父亲肯定会告诉你
all she reveals.
今天怎么总是有人违抗我的命令
Is my will to be defied at every turn?
我不是说了 等打完了仗
Did I not tell you that wanted moment
我自然会找你吗
would find you at battle's end?
我知道我来是坏了您的规矩
I know my presence stands in violation of rule,
但我迫不及待想要见您
yet I could not wait upon the hour to see you.
喝了吧 暖和暖和
Drink, see yourself warmed.
谢谢
Gratitude.
现在暴雪肆虐 无法送你回希留爱沙
Storm's fury stays hand in returning you to Sinuessa.
等势头减弱些
At first sign of its passing,
恺撒会亲自把你送到城内
Caesar himself shall see you again to safety of city walls.
等您回罗马时 我就留在那里吗
Where I am to remain when you return to Rome,
被您永远地抛弃掉
forever banished from your arms.
抛弃
Banished?
你误会了
You mistake intent.
希留爱沙就是为你夺来的
I claimed Sinuessa for you.
这样我要去见你的时候就有地方了
So that we may have a place to ourselves when I am to visit,
随时可去 不受监视 避开闲言蜚语
frequently, far from jealous eyes and wagging tongues.
这不是惩罚 是礼物
It is not punishment, but gift.
你将受我名号的恩泽
You shall rise as my name does,
成为克拉苏家族在希留爱沙的女管家
as vilica of the House of Crassus in Sinuessa.
服侍提比略
Beneath Tiberius.
他会在你身边
He will be beside you,
你可以陪伴他 以你的智慧指导他
receiving benefit of your company and wisdom.
像你对我一样
As I so often have.
我知道他很看重你
I know how much he cares for you.
我知道你也关心他
And you for him.
你把他从青涩懵懂的男孩变成了
You've helped move him from the boy he was
今日的男人
to the man he is.
我想不出还有谁比你更适合辅佐他了
I can think of no one more suited to further guide him.
若是他达不到您的期望
I fear the prospect of blame,
恐怕您要怪罪于我了
should you find him less than expected.
不用担心
Strike worry.
这我们无从预料
It is a thing beyond imagining.
他曾经无药可救 令您大为失望
He has proved bitter disappointment in the past,
不是吗
has he not?
提比略的确犯过大错
It is true that Tiberius fell to grievous error.
我也曾怒发冲冠 暴跳如雷
And I to wrath threatening to shake the heavens.
但现在我们父子同心
Yet we now stand as one,
我还知道 在我内心
and I know in deepest heart
他毕竟是我心爱的儿子
there is no misstep that would see father
无论犯下什么错 都是可以原谅的
withhold forgiveness from treasured son.
我还以为劝你两句 你便不会泪流满面了
I'd hoped soothing words to stem tide of overflowing tears.
别担心
Pay them no mind.
不过是以前那个傻丫头没流完的泪罢了
They are but lingering shadows of a foolish girl.
作为女人 你只用知道自己想要什么就行了
As long as the woman stands clear to heart's desire.
是的 马科斯
Yes, Marcus.
现在我再清楚不过了
Everything is very clear to me now.
再来人我们就不用担心风雪了
If we take in any more our difficulty
该担心我们没空气可呼吸了
may be lack of air to breathe, not cold or snow.
我倒宁愿挤在一起臭哄哄的
I prefer the pressing of rancid flesh
也不愿意老屌冻成冰
to having cock become as ice.
我他妈的就不能摆脱这混蛋吗
Am I never to be free of this fucking shit?
同样摆脱不了咆哮的狂风和被吹跑的帐篷
Add to storm's bluster and see tent blown from strained mooring.
卡斯特斯
Castus.
斯巴达克斯要我来的
Spartacus commands me here.
我别无选择
Choice is removed from hand.
我有
Yet not from mine.
你要放了我吗
You would see me free?
都是纳西尔的恳求
Action born of Nasir's plea.
要不是他求情 我一刀子捅了你
Know that absent them my blade would be slick with Cilician blood.
多谢
Gratitude.
别露出这种表情
Do not fucking cast that look.
甘尼克斯呢
Where is Gannicus?
他没和你在一起吗
He's not with you?
没
No.
甘尼克斯
Gannicus!
以此鲜血…我们诚恳地…
With this blood... we humbly...
恳请…
entreat...
你怎么没和其他人一起走
Why do you not go with the others?
我必须向诸神献祭
I must give offering...
他们会为我们指引道路
the gods shall reveal path...
你再这么跪下去
They reveal only your death,
指引你走向死路还差不多
if you remain on bended knee!
找地方躲避风雪
Seek shelter!
要么就等着到天上见你们的神吧
Or greet your gods upon the shores of the afterlife!
我找不到他
I could not find him.
我去
I go.
你也会走丢的
You would be lost as well.
甘尼克斯不会被风雪打败
Gannicus will not fall to wind and ice.
他体内的酒热着呢 会为他抵御寒冷的
Wine forever in his blood will keep him warm.
我从不喜欢寒冷的天气
I have never favored the cold.
来毯子下面暖和暖和吧
Share blanket, and see yourself warmed.
我不用
I have no need for it.
你都冻得牙齿打架了
Your teeth threaten to shake from head.
我也是
As do mine.
你伤口疼了吗
Your wound gives pain?
疼痛说明我还活着
It reminds that I yet live.
而我也想要活下去
And choose to continue to do so.
我俩又躲在这么狭小的地方
We again find ourself in pressing space.
疗伤 祈祷死亡别带走我们
Nursing wounds and praying the afterlife does not take us.
你在祈祷吗
You pray now, do you?
祈祷很多事情
Upon many things.
但我不会傻到跪在风雪里
Yet I am not dim of mind to kneel in storm,
向上天放声乞求
raise voice to the heavens.
更不会放自己的血
Nor spill my own blood as offering.
那是献祭
It stood as sacrifice.
为斯巴达克斯
For Spartacus.
你现在把他当成神了吗
You believe him a god now?
我们是代他祈祷
It was made on his behalf.
恳求诸神眷顾他的大业 以及为之献身的人
To plead for his cause and all those devoted to it.
我曾怀疑过你的信仰
I have doubted your belief in days past.
其实是我太傻
Found myself a fool for it
没事
You are safe...
you are safe...
我警告过你 远离我这种人
I have warned you. To stay far from men of my kind.
可我做不到
You ask the impossible.
原谅我
Forgive me.
多少
How many?
将近一千人在暴雪中丧生
Nearly a thousand lost to the storm.
一千
A thousand.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus...
我还担心你也死了
I had feared you among the dead.
诸神怜悯 让我们有地方躲过一劫
The gods took pity, and provided us with needed shelter.
并非所有人都如此幸运
Not all so blessed.
的确不是
No. They were not.
我们寻求上天的帮助
We sought aid from the heavens.
保佑我们远离壕沟与围墙的黑暗
To see us beyond darkness of trench and wall.
这就是诸神的答复
And here stands reply.
诸神虽残酷
Yet in their cruelty,
却也为幸存者指了一条生路
perhaps the gods light way for those yet living.
你丧失理智了
You turned from fucking reason.
我已经清醒了
I have embraced it.
我们要填平壕沟 发起进攻 正如你说的
We shall forge trench and press attack, as you so championed.
当时我们还有那一千个兄弟
When we held yet another thousand men,
如今他们都死了
now forever lost to us.
克拉苏的围墙外还有军队 我们怎么打
And what of the army that awaits beyond Crassus' wall?
我们众寡悬殊
How will we match their number?
也许没有那么悬殊
Perhaps there stands no need.
你有话不直说 遮遮掩掩
You speak in fucking riddles, obscuring truth.
正如克拉苏处处遮掩他的行动
As Crassus obscures all he has done,
每一步都狡诈异常
shrouding his moves in deception.
派来恺撒卧底
Placing Caesar among us.
收买赫拉克里奥帮他
Turning Heracleo to his cause.
吸引我们去他的军帐
Drawing us into trap within his tent.
全都是玩阴的
Nothing is ever as it appears.
那就说出你的想法
Then break fucking thoughts,
不然就滚蛋
or fall from presence.
他的壕沟足够截断我们逃跑的路线
His trench stands barrier enough to halt escape.
为什么还要建一道高不可攀的围墙
Why see it coupled with impossible fortification?
让我们看不见围墙后面有什么
To keep our eyes from what lies beyond it.
或者没有什么
Or what does not.
只要派少数人上围墙便可施展疑兵之计
A few man placed upon wall would give illusion of thousands beyond it.
这正是那只老狐狸的风格
A deception worthy of the man himself.
万一你错了呢
And if you are wrong?
那我们就光荣牺牲
Then we shall embrace a glorious death.
至少没让罗马人从背后捅死
Absent Roman swords in our backs.
你想的没错
Your thoughts were true.
只有几百人
There stand only but a few hundred.
那就用他们的热血温暖寒夜
Let us warm the night with their blood.
卢戈 布瑞克提斯
Lugo! Brictius!
带人给这道围墙开个口子
Take men and see breach made in the wall!
统帅
Imperator!
叛贼突破了围墙
The rebels have breached the wall!
传令军团集合
Command the legion to fall to formation!
快去
Quickly!
我的奴隶送回希留爱沙了吗
Was my slave escorted back to Sinuessa?
没人离开您的大帐 统帅
None left your tent, Imperator.
快点行动
Move quickly,
跟上大部队
and follow the others!
这边
Up here!
四处搜查
Check everywhere!
她跑到叛贼的队伍里了
She has moved to join rebellion?
要是没人送她来 她也没这个机会
An opportunity denied her, had she not been brought to the ridge.
我原以为她是为了…
I thought her to have just cause
汇报
Give report.
围墙上没有岗哨
There stands no sentry upon the wall.
也没看到斯巴达克斯他们
Nor sight of Spartacus and his army.
没道理啊
It holds no sense.
他是怎么跨过壕沟的呢
How could he have spanned trench?
该死的野蛮人
The fucking savage.
他用死人把壕沟填平了
He fills trench with his own dead.
他也只有这一招了
He but seizes means left to him.
他们肯定没跑远
They can not have traveled far a distance.
传令军团前进
Give order to advance the legion.
我要夺回我的…
I would reclaim what is mine
保护统帅
Protect the imperator!
我们必须撤退
We must fall back!
破阵
Break formation!
伟大的克拉苏在我们面前屁滚尿流地跑了
The mighty Crassus shows fucking ass as he flees from us!
他会带着攻城锤和投石器回来的
He will return, with rams and ballistae.
然后发现他到手的功业灰飞烟灭
And find his monument of illusion taken to flame,
而我们远远地甩开了他
lending opportunity to place distance between us.
我们离开这里
Let us see ourselves far from here.
到时候用胜利和马科斯•克拉苏的鲜血
And honor the fallen with future victories...
祭奠我们的死者
and the blood of Marcus Crassus.